<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands ioyalty, in ioyfull expressions, for the City of Londons safety, being a true and reall relation of many most remarkable passages which have been lately divulged by one D. Peake Vicar of Tenterden in Kent, and Parson of Ancridge in the same countie. Who did speak dangerous words against the Parliament, the Lord Maior and aldermen of this City of London, and now presented to the consideration of the Honourable House of Commons in Parliament. / Discovered by Master Minis his late curate there, and now under Master Matthew Milward, of Great Saint Hellens in London.</title>
            <author>Minis, Master.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89163</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2194</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E177_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15356</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859844</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859844</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111944</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89163)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111944)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 31:E177[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands ioyalty, in ioyfull expressions, for the City of Londons safety, being a true and reall relation of many most remarkable passages which have been lately divulged by one D. Peake Vicar of Tenterden in Kent, and Parson of Ancridge in the same countie. Who did speak dangerous words against the Parliament, the Lord Maior and aldermen of this City of London, and now presented to the consideration of the Honourable House of Commons in Parliament. / Discovered by Master Minis his late curate there, and now under Master Matthew Milward, of Great Saint Hellens in London.</title>
                  <author>Minis, Master.</author>
                  <author>Milward, Matthias, fl. 1603-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R.H. for I.H. at his house in the Old-Bayley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Peake, Humphrey, d. 1645 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Commons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sedition --  England --  Kent --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111944:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Englands Ioyalty, IN Ioyfull expreſsions, for the City of <hi>Londons</hi> ſafety, being a true and reall Relation of many moſt remarkable paſſages which have been lately divulged by one D. <hi>Peake</hi> Vicar of <hi>Tenterden</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> and Parſon of <hi>Ancridge</hi> in the ſame Countie.</p>
            <p>Who did ſpeak dangerous words againſt the Parliament, the Lord Maior and Aldermen of this City of <hi>London,</hi> and now preſented to the conſideration of the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS in PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>Diſcovered by Maſter <hi>Minis</hi> his late Curate there, and now under Maſter <hi>Matthew Milward,</hi> of Great Saint <hi>Hellens</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R.H.</hi> for <hi>I.H.</hi> at his houſe in the Old-Bayley. 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:111944:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111944:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Doctour <hi>Peake</hi> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted into my Lords Grace of <hi>Canterburies</hi> favour: he was fortthwith advanced to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, being made one of his Majeſties Chaplaines in Ordinary, a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bend of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and tvvo other ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Promotions, the one being the Vicarage of <hi>Tenderden,</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and the other the Parſonage of <hi>Ancridge,</hi> ſome ſeven miles from thence diſtant, and both theſe of a very good yearly value, he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe very ſeldome preaching, and then after the <hi>Arminian</hi> garbe, he allowing but a ſmall ſtipend to his Curate, whoſe chance then to be, was Maſter <hi>Minis,</hi> till better promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould befall him.</p>
            <p>About ſome fourteen weekes ſince the ſaid Maſter <hi>Minis,</hi> being at dinner with
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111944:3"/>Doctour <hi>Peake</hi> and his Wife; Doctour <hi>Peakes</hi> Wives Father, and another Widow-woman, by name Miſtris <hi>Gee,</hi> the Wife of the late Miniſter of <hi>Tenterden,</hi> when after din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Doctour falling into diſcouſe with his Wives father, uttered many baſe and ſcandalous ſpeeches againſt the State, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the death of the late Earle of <hi>Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and then fell to diſcourſe of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the trained Bands of the City, his Wife ſaid they were a company of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly fellowes, and he replied, that a Company of five hundred good Souldiers out of <hi>Ireland</hi> would quickely vanquiſh them all, and put them to flight, and ſaid moreover, that it were a good deed to take the Lord Maior, the Sheriffes, and ſome of the Aldermen, with others of good ranke and quality, and hange them up at their owne doores, the reſt would ſoon be brought to ſubjection.</p>
            <p>O the inveterate, malitious, and cancred rotten heart of this ungodly Doctour! ſo uncharitable, to wiſh evill to that honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111944:3"/>City, where he had his firſt well-being, in ſupplying a Lecture in Saint <hi>Bartholomews</hi> Church behinde the <hi>Exchange</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> Doctour <hi>Grant</hi> being the now Miniſter thereof. I beſeech Almighty God to make this hollow-hearted, evill-thoughted Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour to be brought to deſerved puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>His Wives father out of baſe diſpoſition and venomous heart, vviſhed vvith great violence and paſſion, that the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> vvere burnt, and ſome of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment taken and hanged: but marke the juſt judgement of God upon this wicked miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creant, for that afternoon he went to his ovvne houſe ſome ſeven miles from thence and the next day died ſuddenly, the Doctor hearing of theſe traiterous ſpeeches never rebuked him therefore.</p>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch like wicked and traiterous ſpeeches were taken notice of by Maſter <hi>Minis,</hi> and by him upon the faith of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, are ready by oath to be maintained againſt the ſaid Doctour to the Houſe of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111944:4"/>Commons in Parliament, who no doubt will ſpeedily ſend for the ſaid Doctour, and according to his demerits make him an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample for all ſuch ill-affected people to Church and State to take warning by.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Maſter <hi>Minis</hi> doth alſo teſtifie, that formerly he hath been an inſtrument of the apprehenſion of divers Prieſts and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, which the Lords Grace of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> did under a colour ſend his Warrant for, and they were the next day releaſed, which Maſter <hi>Minis</hi> taking notice of, he went to <hi>Croydon,</hi> the Archbiſhop then lying there, and told his Grace of the ſame, who anſwered him, they had the Queenes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and that he could not ſtay any of them, that were by her protected: this was all he had for his paines and care in ſeeking to diſcover ſuch; onely his dinner there, and a twenty ſhillings peece to ſtop his mouth as the Biſhop then thought. But now thankes be given to the Almighty God, the times are altered, and the honourable Parliament have made good and wholeſome orders, for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111944:4"/>the apprehending of Prieſts and Ieſuits, with promiſes to all ſuch as ſhall be the meanes of diſcovering of them, or any ſuch.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <p>THe aforementioned Relation was exactly taken from Maſter <hi>Minos</hi> owne mouth, by the teſtification of many ſufficient witneſſes, and now publiſhed to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſpectacle of the world, to demonſtrate unto all the treacherous and Antichriſtian exoptations of the Conter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burian Doctour: but I hope the Parliament will take theſe invective aſperſions of ſuch railing <hi>Rabſhakehs</hi> into their grave and judicious conſiderations; and I fear that the ſame curſes which they wiſh againſt this renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned City will light ſhortly on their owne heads; while my daily and continuall prayers ſhall be, that God of his Almighty Omnipotence would preſerve and defend this City and noble Parliament, to the extirpation of all ſuch hereticall Doctours, and the flouriſhing eſtate of this whole Kingdome.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
